Guide to the Ester Hernandez Papers
Department of Special Collections
- Art Organizations, Series 9; 3 linear ft.
  - Wright Gallery, UCLA: "CARA - Chicano Art - Resistance and Affirmation" [1] (Box 80, Folder 3)
    National Chicano Screenprint Taller, 1988-1989, in conjunction with Self Help Graphics. Miscellaneous information, correspondence, agreements, brochure, etc.
  - Wright Gallery, UCLA: "CARA - Chicano Art - Resistance and Affirmation" [2] (Box 80, Folder 4)
    Miscellaneous correspondence, brochures, invitations, reviews, contracts, flyers,announcements, folios, newspapers, magazines, agreements, etc., 1990s. [1 of 2]
  - Wright Gallery, UCLA: "CARA - Chicano Art - Resistance and Affirmation" [3] (Box 80, Folder 5)
    Miscellaneous correspondence, brochures, invitations, reviews, contracts, flyers,announcements, folios, newspapers, magazines, agreements, etc., 1990s. [2 of 2]
  - UC-Santa Barbara, "Project Caridad" [1 of 2] (Box 80, Folder 6)
    Miscellaneous correspondence, brochures, catalogs, agreements.
  - UC-Santa Barbara, "Project Caridad" [2 of 2] (Box 80, Folder 7)
- Art Publications and Books, Series 10; 5 linear ft.
  In Series 10, anthologies, chap books, paperbacks, and other published material collected by Hernandez are found. A number of the items are autographed and inscribed by the authors, or feature images produced by Hernandez, interviews with or critical analysis of her work.
  - Alarcon, Francisco X. Loma Prieta (We Press, Santa Cruz, CA), 1990 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    Includes earlier work Quake Poems; autographed and inscribed by author.
  - Alarcon, Francisco X. Quake Poems (We Press, Santa Cruz, CA), 1989; chap book (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Bergmann, Emilie L. and Smith, Paul julian, eds.Entiendes: Queer Readings, Hispanic Writings, Duke University Press, Durham, NC, 1995 (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Bernstein, Robin, and Silberman, Seth Clark, eds. Generation Q: gays, lesbians, and bisexuals born around 1969's Stonewall riots tell their stories of growing up in the age of information (Box 81, Folder 4)
  - Carvalho, Josely, et al. Heresies Latina, A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics, vol 7 no 3 issue 27, New York (n.d.) (Box 81, Folder 5)
  - Castillo, Ana. the Mixquiahuala Letters (Bilingual Press, SUNY-Binghamton, NY), 1986 (Box 81, Folder 6)
    Autographed and inscribed
  - Corpi, Lucha. Palabras de Mediodia/ Noon Words: Poems by Lucha Corpi Rodriguez-Nieto, Catherine, translator (El Fuego de Aztlan Publications, UC Berkeley, CA), 1987 (Box 81, Folder 7)
  - Curiel, Babara Brinson. Speak To Me From Dreams. Third Woman Press, Berkeley, CA, 1989 (Box 82, Folder 1)
    Autographed and inscribed by author.
  - de la Garza, Luis Alberto, compiler. Preliminary Chicano and Latino Lesbian and Gay Bibliography, "El Arte Sana," Mission Cultural Center, SF, 1994 (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - Drescher, Tim, and Goldman, Ruth. A Survey of East Bay Murals of the 1970s, 1980 (Box 82, Folder 3)
    Draft
  - Duarte, Lourdes Sanchez. Inclinense, inclinense (Editorial Factor, Naucalpan de Juarez, Mexico), 1995 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Handel, Jane. Swimming on Dry Land: The Memories of an Ascetic Libertine (Spider Woman Press, San Francisco, CA), 1990 (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Hernandez, Guillermo. Canciones de la Raza: Songs of the Chicano Experience (El Fuego de Aztlan, UC Berkeley, CA), 1978 (Box 82, Folder 6)
    Songbook
  - Leibowitz, Herbert, ed. Parnassus, Poetry in Review, vol 20 no 1 and 2, 1995 (Box 82, Folder 7)
  - Lopez, Erika. Lap Dancing for Mommy (Seal Press, Seattle, WA), 1997 (Box 82, Folder 8)
  - Lopez, Yolanda M. Works: 1975-1978 (Exhibit catalog, Mandeville Center for the Arts, La Jolla, CA) (Box 82, Folder 9)
    Autographed and inscribed by author ["For Irene..."[Perez?]]
  - Lumsden, Ian. Homosexuality: Society and the State in Mexico, Canadian Gay Archives, Toronto, CA, 1991 (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Montoya, Jose. Information - 20 Years of Joda (Chusma House Publications, San Jose, CA), 1992 (Box 83, Folder 2)
  - Montoya, Jose. El Sol Y Los De Abajo and other R.C.A.F. poems[*] (Ediciones Pocho-Che, San Francisco, CA), 1972; newspaper (Box 83, Folder 3)
    *[RCAF: Rebel Chicano Art Front alias The Royal Chicano Air Force]
  - Moraga, Cherrie. The Last Generation: Prose and Poetry, South End Press, Boston,MA, 1993 (Box 83, Folder 4)
  - Moraga, Cherrie. Loving in the War Years (south end press, Boston, MA), 1983 (Box 83, Folder 5)
  - Morales, Rodolfo. Juegos y Evocaciones (Exhibit catalog, The Mexican Museum, San Francisco, CA), 1996 (Box 83, Folder 6)
    Autographed.
  - Noriega, Chon A., ed. Chicanos and Film: Representation and Resistance, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, MN, 1992 (Box 83, Folder 7)
  - Ochoa, Maria, and Teaiwa, Teresa, eds. Enunciating Our Terms:Women of Color in Collaboratoion and Conflict. (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - Palmer, William J., ed. Contested Spaces in the Carribbean and the Americas:Modern Fiction Studies, Purdue University, Spring, 1998 (Box 84, Folder 2)
  - Portillo, Christina, et al.Bibliography of Writings on La Mujer, UC Berkeley, 1976 (Box 84, Folder 3)
  - Rebolledo, Tey Diana. Women Singing in the Snow: A Cultural Analysis of Chicana Literature, University of Arizona Press, Tucson, AZ, 1995 (Box 84, Folder 4)
  - Rebolledo, Tey Diana, and Rivero, Eliana S., eds. Infinite Divisions: An Anthology of Chicana Literature (The University of Arizona Press, Tucson, AZ), 1993 (Box 84, Folder 5)
    Autographed and inscribed by Rebolledo
  - Reynoso, Antonio Gonzalez, curator/ed. Frida Kahlo, 1907-1954: The Collection of Dolores Olmedo Patino (exhibit catalog, Plaza de la Raza, Los Angeles, CA), 1987 (Box 84, Folder 6)
    Autographed and inscribed by translators Holly Barnet-Sanchez, Marcos T. Sanchez
  - Roscoe, Will, ed. Living the Spirit: A Gay American Indian Anthology, 1988 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Roth, Moira, ed. Connecting Conversations: Interviews with 28 Bay Area Women Artists, Eucalyptus Press, Oakland, CA, 1988 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Rubio, Celia de la Riva. Lagrinas y Cadenas/ Chains and Tears: Gay Feminist Prose and Poetry, Morelia, MX, 1994 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - Soto, Gary. Small Faces (Arte Publico, University of Houston, TX), 1986 (Box 85, Folder 4)
    Autographed
  - Trujillo, Carla, ed. Chicana Lesbians: The Girls Our Mothers Warned Us About, Third Woman Press, Berkeley, CA, 1991 (2 copies) (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - Trujillo, Carla, ed. Living Chicana Theory, Third Woman Press, Berkeley, Ca, 1998 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Villanueva, Tino, ed. Imagine - International Chicano Poetry Journal; Arte Chicano Issue, Summer Winter, 1986, Boston, MA (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - a la brava: A Queer Latino/a Zine, Issue #1, January, 19967; Issue #3, Winter 1996/1997 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Americas and Latinas: A Journal of Women and Gender, 1995 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The Art of Provocation; Ester Hernandez, A Retrospective, exhibition monograph, CN Gorman Museum, UC Davis, 1995 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Art of the Other Mexico: Sources and Meaning, exhibit catalog, The Mexican Fine Arts Museum, Chicago, 1993-1995 (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Bearing Witness/Sobre Viviendo: Anthology of Native American and Latina Women, CALYX: A Journal of Art and Literature by Women, Vol. 8 No. 2, Corvallis, OR, Spring, 1984 (Box 86, Folder 7)
    includes work by Ester Hernandez, Cherrie Moraga, Julia Alvarez, Linda Lomahaftewa, Lillian Pitt, Paula Gunn Allen, etc.
  - Calacas del Taller Grafica Popular, 1989; newspaper (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - Ceremony of Memory: New Expressions in Spirituality Among Contemporary Hispanic Artists, exhibition guide, Center for Contemporary Arts, Santa Fe, NM, 1988 (Box 87, Folder 2)
  - Cipactli: San Francisco State University, Winter/Spring 1995 [autographed and inscribed by Juanita Chavez, daughter of Dolores Huerta] (Box 87, Folder 3)
  - Day of the Dead - the Tex/Mex Tradition (exhibit catalog, The Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center, San Antonio, TX; booklet attributed to Kay Turner and Pat Jasper), 1988 (Box 87, Folder 4)
  - Dia de los Muertos: exhibition held at the Alternative Museum, New York City, NY (Box 87, Folder 5)
    An exhibition based on the Mexican and Central American annual tradition celebrating and honoring the dead, co-curated by the Alternative Museum and Galeria de la Raza and the Mission Cultural Center, SF; exhibition catalog includes work by Mariana Yampo
  - Evocando El Paraiso: Reflections on the Works of Cristina Emmanuel, monograph, Galeria de la Raza, San Francisco, March 1989 (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - En Frequencia: monthly bi-lingual magazine and program guide, KBBF, FM 89, December 1979, January 1980 (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - Encuentro: Invasion of the Americas and the Making of the Mestizo, exhibition guide, SPARC (Social and Public Aret Resource Center), Venice, CA, 1991 (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - Ester Hernandez, monograph, Galeria de la Raza, June, 1988 (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - Ex profeso: recuento de afinidades colectiva plastica contemporanea, exhibit guide, Museo Universitario del Chopo, MX, 1989 (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - Fiberarts: The Magazine of Textiles, Sept/Oct 1995, vol 22 no. 2 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    [pg. 19, New Works: The Sacred Jump, tapestry by Consuelo Jimenez Underwood?]
  - Florilegia: a Retrospective, CALYX: A Journal of Art and Literature by Women, Corvallis, OR, 1987 (Box 87, Folder 12)
    Includes work by Ester Hernandez, Julia Alvarez, Pat Mora, Margaret Randall, Gail Tremblay, and many others.
  - La Frontera/The Border: Art About the Mexico/United States Border Experience, exhibition guide, Museum of Contemporary Art, San Diego, 1993 (Box 87, Folder 13)
  - Con To' Los Hierros: A Retrospective of the Work of Pepon Osorio, exhibition guide, El Museo del Barrio, New York, 1991 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Dia De Los Muertos, Mexican Fine Arts Center Museum (Chicago) catalog covering exhibits 1987-1990 (Box 88, Folder 2)
  - Francisco Toledo: A Retrospective of his Graphic Works, exhibition guide, Mexican Fine Arts Center Museum, Chicago, 1988 (Box 88, Folder 3)
  - Biombo Negro: La Revista de los Comensales del Crimen, vol 1 no. 5, April -May, 1993(?), Mexico, D.F. (Box 88, Folder 4)
  - Biombo Negro: La Revista de los Comensales del Crimen, vol 2 no. 8, November- December, 1994, Mexico, D.F. (Box 88, Folder 5)
  - Intimate Lives, Women and Their Work: Work by Ten Contemporary Latina Artists, exhibition guide,Austin, TX, ca. 1990 (Box 89, Folder 1)
  - La Morena 1993: Women of Color in the Arts, Datebook Calendar, Morena Newspaper, Berkeley, CA. (Box 89, Folder 2)
    Dedicated to the memory of Eva Carole Garcia; featuring Amy Tan, Terry MacMillan, Faith Ringold, janice Mirikitani, Sandra Cisneros, Rosie Perez, Ester Hernandez, Sonia Sanchez, Lorraine Hansberry, Jean LaMarr, Guadalupe Garcia, etc.
  - Les Voz: Revista de Cultura Lesbica Feminista, para todos las mujeres, No 9 Diciembre - Enero, Algarin, MX, 1998[?] (Box 89, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Writings: pre-Colubian Goddesses (Box 89, Folder 4)
  - Mutual Influences/Influencias Mutuas, exhibition guide, Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center, San Antonio, TX, (n.d.) (Box 89, Folder 5)
  - Parnassus: Poetry in Review, vol 17, no. 1, New York, NY, 1992 (Box 89, Folder 6)
    Features work by: Ester Hernandez, Carmen Lomas Garza, Yong Soon Min,Carrie Mae Weems, etc.
  - Past Presence: A Circle of Women's Vision, 1987 (Box 89, Folder 7)
    Catalog exhibition, Corvallis Arts Center, Oregon; Hernandez mentioned as exhibitor
  - Photographic Memories of an Aboriginal Savant - Hulleah J. Tsinhnahjinnie, exhibit brochure, UC Davis, 1994 (Box 89, Folder 8)
  - Portfolio: American Indian Contemporary Arts, 1986 (Box 89, Folder 9)
  - Portfolio: American Indian Contemporary Arts III, 1991 (Box 89, Folder 10)
  - Primera Antologia del Archivo Popular de la Mujer, Department of Spanish and Portuguese, Stanford University, n.d. (Box 89, Folder 11)
  - Quincentennial Articles (Box 89, Folder 12)
  - The Resurrection of Miguel Marmol, booklet with selected text from Eduardo Galeano's the Century of Wind (Box 89, Folder 13)
  - Rethinking Columbus - Teaching About the 500th Anniversary of Columbus' Arrival in America (Box 89, Folder 14)
  - "A Salute to Latinas in the Arts," Crossroads, May 1993 (Box 89, Folder 15)
  - Santa Barraza (exhibit catalog, Galeria Posada, Sacramento, CA), 1992 (Box 90, Folder 1)
  - El Teatro Campesino: The First Twenty Years...., 1985 (Box 90, Folder 2)
    Booklet produced for Twentieth Anniversary Celebration, held at the Westin St. Francis Hotel, San Francisco.
  - Venus Envy Chapter One, Amalia Mesa-Baines, exhibit guide, Whitnet Museum of Art, New York,1993 (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Ya Vas, Carnal: Poetry by Rodrigo Reyes, Francisco X. Alarcon, Juan Pablo Gutierrez (Humanizarte Publications, San Francisco, CA), 1985 (Box 90, Folder 4)
    Autographed and inscribed by authors Reyes and Gutierrez
- United Farm Workers, Series 11; 2.5 linear ft.
  A member of the United Farm Workers of America, Hernandez collected material and took photographs of marches, demonstrations, and appearances by UFW leaders, which appear in Series 11. In particular, she documented the funeral of Cesar Chavez and the subsequent Peregrenacion march in honor of Chavez, mostly in slides. Hernandez also recorded in film her friendship with Dolores Huerta, co-founder and First Vice President Emeritus of the UFW. A short subseries contains UFW documentary films in VHS format, and audiocassettes of radio broadcast discussions and tributes at the time of Cesar Chavez's death in 1993.
  - General Information, etc., Subseries 11.1
    - UFWA: miscellaneous flyers, posters, and bumber stickers (Box 90, Folder 5)
    - Cesar Chavez: Keep Cesar Chavez St. Campaign, 1995; flyer autographed by Dolores Huerta (Box 90, Folder 6)
    - UFW: California Rural Legal Assistance, miscellaneous (Box 90, Folder 7)
    - UFW: Boycott Grapes - 25th Anniversary Commemorative Magazine, 1987 (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - UFW:Songbook (Box 90, Folder 9)
    - Cesar Chavez: Memorial Press Packet, 1993 (Box 90, Folder 10)
    - UFW: Miscellanous newspapers (Box 90, Folder 11)
    - UFW: Memorabilia (Box 90, Folder 12)
    - UFW: Ester Hernandez's membership card and related information (Box 90, Folder 13)
    - Pesticide Education Center - Dr. Marion Moses (Box 90, Folder 14)
    - McFarland - Cancer cluster - miscellaneous articles (Box 90, Folder 15)
    - Kettleman City - Incinerator (Box 90, Folder 16)
    - UFW: Peregrinacion/Pilgrimage, march from Delano to Sacramento, March 31-April 24, 1994, 1993 (Box 91, Folder 1)
      Newspaper articles and ephemera
    - UFWA: miscellaneous brochures, memos, media handouts, articles, etc., 1987-1988 (Box 91, Folder 2)
    - UFWA: miscellaneous articles, brochures, handouts, ephemera, etc., 1992-1994 (Box 91, Folder 3)
    - UFWA: miscellaneous publications: Food and Justice; El Macriado, 1987-1990 (Box 91, Folder 4)
    - UFWA: Coloring and song books (Box 91, Folder 5)
  - Cesar Chavez, Subseries 11.2
    - Cesar Chavez: photocopies of news articles regarding Chavez's death, 1993; photocopies (Box 91, Folder 6)
    - Cesar Chavez: miscellaneous news articles on street name change, 1993; photocopies (Box 91, Folder 7)
    - Cesar Chavez: memorial brochure; Prayer of the Farmworkers' Struggle, photocopies (Box 91, Folder 8)
    - Cesar Chavez's Funeral; Peregrancion March: photographs (Box 92, Folder 1)
    - Cesar Chavez's Funeral; Peregrancion March: negatives (Box 92, Folder 2)
    - Cesar Chavez's Funeral: slides (Box 92, Folder 3)
    - UFW Peregranacion March: slides [1 of 2] (Box 92, Folder 4)
    - UFW Peregranacion March: slides [2 of 2] (Box 92, Folder 5)
  - Dolores Huerta, Subseries 11.3
    - Dolores Huerta: miscellaneous articles and announcements (Box 93, Folder 1)
    - Dolores Huerta: and Richard Chavez's children, miscellaneous material concerning Camilla and Juanita (Box 93, Folder 2)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs of Cinco de Mayo celebration, UC Santa Cruz, 1985 (Box 93, Folder 3)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs of birthday parties, etc. (Box 93, Folder 4)
    - Dolores Huerta: slides, march on Cesar Chavez Boulevard, San Francisco, April, 1995 (Box 93, Folder 5)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs, Fight the Radical Right March, San Francisco, 1996 (Box 93, Folder 6)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs, ca. 1996 (Box 93, Folder 7)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs, Berkeley, CA, ca. 1990 [?] (Box 93, Folder 8)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs, ca. 1998 (Box 93, Folder 9)
    - Dolores Huerta: photographs, 67th birthday party, 1999 (Box 93, Folder 10)
    - Dolores Huerta: miscellaneous slides, photographs, n.d. (Box 93, Folder 11)
    - Dolores Huerta: computer printouts of Huerta photo (2), n.d. (Box 93, Folder 12)
  - Audio-Visual, Subseries 11.4
    - No Grapes, documentary regarding negative health effects of pesticde use, narrated by Mike Farrell, produced for the United Farm Workers, 1992, 13:34 [copy of above], VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 2)
    - Uvas No, documentary in Spanish regarding negative health effects of pesticde use, narrated by Ricardo Montalban, produced for the United Farm Workers, 1992, 13:34, VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 3)
    - Harvest of Sorrow - Part 1 "Field of Workers," n.d., VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 4)
    - Strawberries: The Fruit of Injustice, United Farm Workers, n.d. VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - Cesar Chavez's Funeral, night before march, unedited, 1993, VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 6)
    - Cesar E. Chavez: Celebration of Life, 1927-1993, 1993[?], VHS cassette (Box 94, Folder 7)
    - Tribute to Cesar Chavez: KPFA radio broadcast, Chuy[?], Amalia Gonzalez, 3 audio cassettes, 9/17/1993. (Box 94, Folder 8)